Guide to the Coletta Youngers Papers, 1977-2004 and undated, bulk 1983-1998
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Coletta Youngers papers 1977-2004 and undated bulk 1983-1998
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Youngers, Coletta
19.7 linear feet Extent: 9825 Items
Human rights researcher and policy advocate at the Washington Office on Latin America. The Coletta Youngers Papers span the dates 1977-2004, and consist of reports and scholarly research, clippings, correspondence, and government documents related to socio-political conditions and human rights issues in Perú, gathered by Youngers while living in Peru during the 1980s and researching her 2003 book on political violence in Perú. The collection is divided into the Printed Material and the Subject Files Series; there is also a separate listing at the end of this finding aid of printed works transferred to the Duke University Perkins Library general collections. Beyond the research materials in these series, there are currently no additional personal papers of Youngers in the collection. The Printed Material Series contains published reports on human rights circulated by a wide variety of organizations working inside and outside Perú. Most of the Perú-based human rights organizations are connected with the Coordinadora de Derechos Humanos (CNDDHH), an umbrella human rights organization based in Lima. Youngers' research files on human rights issues and a subseries of Peruvian and Latin American serial publications complete the Printed Material Series. The Subject Files Series contains files and informal reports of the CNDDHH and associated human rights organizations, most notably the Asociación Pro Derechos Humanos (APRODEH), El Centro de Asesoría Laboral del Perú (CEDAL), and the Instituto Defensa Legal (IDL). Further documentation of human rights abuses by government and rebel factions, drug policy files, papers related to former Peruvian president Alberto Fujimori's security advisor Vladimiro Montesinos, and the Maoist guerrilla group Sendero Luminoso complete the collection. Material in this collection documents the complex links between Peruvian government policy and international pressure, and the violent tactics employed by revolutionary groups as well as agents of the Peruvian government. Further, it chronicles the consequences of those actions, especially for rural and indigenous populations and local human rights advocates. The collection also contains numerous U.S. government documents obtained through the Freedom of Information Act which give insight into U.S. diplomacy, military and drug policy. Substantial portions of the collection are in Spanish. Acquired as part of the Human Rights Archive.
RL.01424
Language: Material in English and Spanish
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
The bulk of the collection is open to research, however Accession (2008-0151) is CLOSED for 25 years.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. The library may require up to 48 hours to retrieve these materials for research use.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Provenance
The Coletta A. Youngers Papers were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a gift in July 2007.
Biographical Note
1975 Washington Office on Latin America (WOLA) founded
1980 Sendero Luminoso (Shining Path), Maoist guerrilla group, became active in Perú
1982 Youngers interned at Washington Office on Latin American (WOLA)
1983 Eight Peruvian journalists killed at Uchuraccay
1985 Youngers earned a Masters Degree in Public Affairs at the Woodrow Wilson School at Princeton University Coordinadora Nacional de Derechos Humanos founded in Perú
1985-1987 Youngers served as Project Manager at the Perú-Chile Office of the Catholic Relief Services, where she developed, monitored and evaluated rural and urban development and human rights projects by Peruvian NGO's
1987 Youngers began working at Washington Office on Latin America (WOLA); currently monitors, analyzes, and disseminates information on political developments, human rights and U.S. Policy in the Andean region of South America
1990 Alberto Fujimori elected president of Perú
1992 Fujimori dismissed Peruvian legislative and judicial branches in "self coup"
1997 Youngers published Reluctant recruits: The U.S. military and the war on drugs (August) (WOLA), and The only war we've got: Drug enforcement in Latin America, NACLA Report on the Americas, Vol. I, No. 2 (September/October) (WOLA)
1998 Youngers published Drug Certification Doesn't Make the Grade in The Christian Science Monitor (February 17)
2000 Youngers published Deconstructing Democracy: Perú Under President Alberto Fujimori (WOLA) Fujimori resigned in the wake of public outcry over an election bribery scandal involving his advisor Vladimiro Montesinos
2002 Youngers published Collateral Damage: U.S. Drug Control in the Andes (WOLA) and Perú's Coordinadora Nacional de Derechos Humanos: A Case Study in Coalition Building (WOLA)
2003 Youngers published Violencia Politica y Sociedad Civil en el Perú: Historia de la Coordinadora Nacional de Derechos Humanos
2005 Youngers co-edited, with Eileen Rosin, Drugs and Democracy in Latin America: The Impact of U.S. Policy, which came out of the Drugs, Democracy, and Human Rights (DDHR) project directed by Youngers and Rosin at WOLA
2006 Montesinos, Fujimori advisor, sentenced to 20 years in prison for arms trafficking
2007 Fujimori extradited to Perú to stand trial for his involvement in massacres and "disappearances" at Los Barrios Altos and La Cantuta
Collection Overview
The Coletta Youngers Papers span the dates 1977-2004, and consist of reports and scholarly research, clippings, correspondence, and government documents related to socio-political conditions and human rights issues in Perú, gathered by Youngers while living in Peru during the 1980s and researching her 2003 book on political violence in Perú. The collection is divided into the Printed Material and the Subject Files Series; there is also a separate listing at the end of this finding aid of printed works transferred to the Duke University Perkins Library general collections. Beyond the research materials in these series, there are currently no additional personal papers of Youngers in the collection. The Printed Material Series contains published reports on human rights circulated by a wide variety of organizations working inside and outside Perú. Most of the Perú-based human rights organizations are connected with the Coordinadora de Derechos Humanos (CNDDHH), an umbrella human rights organization based in Lima. Youngers' research files on human rights issues and a subseries of Peruvian and Latin American serial publications complete the Printed Material Series. The Subject Files Series contains files and informal reports of the CNDDHH and associated human rights organizations, most notably the Asociación Pro Derechos Humanos (APRODEH), El Centro de Asesoría Laboral del Perú (CEDAL), and the Instituto Defensa Legal (IDL). Further documentation of human rights abuses by government and rebel factions, drug policy files, papers related to former Peruvian president Alberto Fujimori's security advisor Vladimiro Montesinos, and the Maoist guerrilla group Sendero Luminoso complete the collection. Material in this collection documents the complex links between Peruvian government policy and international pressure, and the violent tactics employed by revolutionary groups as well as agents of the Peruvian government. Further, it chronicles the consequences of those actions, especially for rural and indigenous populations and local human rights advocates. The collection also contains numerous U.S. government documents obtained through the Freedom of Information Act which give insight into U.S. diplomacy, military and drug policy. Substantial portions of the collection are in Spanish. Aquired as part of the Human Rights Archive.
Subject Headings
Youngers, Coletta; Fujimori, Alberto; Montesinos Torres, Vladimiro; APRODEH (Organization); El Centro de Asesoría Laboral del Perú.; Coordinadora Nacional de Derechos Humanos (Perú); Instituto Defensa Legal; Washington Office on Latin America; Drug policy; Drug production, illicit; Fujimori, Alberto -- Press coverage -- Perú.; Human rights -- Perú; Human rights -- Perú--Cases; Human rights -- Perú--History -- 20th century; Perú--History -- 1980-; Perú--History -- Autonomy and independence movements; Perú -- Politics and government -- 1980-; Sendero Luminoso (Guerrilla group) -- History; Sendero Luminoso (Guerrilla group) -- Press coverage; Communist parties -- Perú.; United States -- Foreign relations -- Perú.; Human Rights Archive; Machine-readable records
Contents of Collection
- Printed Material Series, 1978-2002 and undated, (13 boxes)
  Separated into Human Rights Reports, Research Files, and Serials subseries. The Human Rights Reports Subseries is further divided into reports by organizations headquartered in Perú and international human rights solidarity organizations. In the Peruvian Organizations grouping, reports by prominent organizations such as the Asociación Nacional de Familiares de Secuestrados Detenidos y Desaparacidos del Perú (ANFASEP), the Asociación Pro Derechos Humanos (APRODEH), El Centro de Asesoría Laboral del Perú (CEDAL), the Comisión Andina de Juristas (CAJ), the Comisión de Derechos Humanos (CODEH), the Comisión Episcopal de Acción Social (CEAS), the Comisión Nacional de Derechos Humanos (CONADEH), Coordinadora Nacional de Derechos Humanos (CNDDHH), Defensoria del Pueblo, and the Instituto Defensa Legal (IDL) are included, among others. Reports by major international human rights organizations are included in the International Solidarity Organizations grouping. Of these, Amnesty International and Human Rights Watch (as well as Americas Watch) are the major contributors. Numerous occasional papers and conference proceedings from institutions based in the United States, including the Washington Office on Latin America (WOLA), also appear in this grouping as do reports by organizations based in Canada and the United Kingdom. Additional conference papers and proceedings as well as drafts of articles on Perú by scholars in anthropology, history, and political science make up the Research Files Subseries. Topics covered in this series include case study articles of human rights abuses, articles on the communist revolutionary movements Sendero Luminoso and the Movimiento Revolucionario Túpac Amaru (MRTA), and peasant-organized village protection movements (rondas). The Serials Subseries consists of magazines and journals chiefly printed by Peruvian media and advocacy organizations. These include runs of issues of the Andean Newsletter (published by the CAJ) from 1993-1998, Cuestion de Estado from 1992-2001, Flecha en el Azul, Ideele (published by IDL) from 1991-2000, and selected issues of Debate, Iglesia en Sicuani, Paginas, and Perú Hoy. A number of single issues of serial publications may be found in this subseries as well. The publications in this subseries focus on Peruvian economy, society, and politics, with publications on rondas, socioeconomic development, Sendero Luminoso and the MRTA included. The Human Rights Reports and Research Files subseries are organized as received; the Serials Subseries is organized alphabetically by title and chronologically within each title. Some materials have been moved to the Oversize Materials.
  - Human Rights Reports Subseries, 1978-2002 and undated (Box 1-4)
  - Research Files Subseries, 1983-2002 and undated (Box 4-7)
    [Some items removed to Oversize Material.]
  - Serials Subseries, 1981-2002 and undated, (6 boxes) (Box 4-7)
    - Andean Newsletter-Cuestion de Estado, 1992-1994 (Box 8)
    - Cuestion de Estado, 1995-2001-IDEAS-Programa Piura (Box 9)
    - Ideele, 1991-1995 June (Box 10)
    - Ideele, 1995 July-1998 July (Box 11)
    - Ideele, 1998 Aug.-2000 Jan.-Ninas y Adolescencias (Box 12)
    - Paginas-Viaje a Eutanasia (Box 13)
- Subject Files Series, 1977-2004 and undated, (18 boxes) (Box 13)
  Divided into the following subseries: Coordinadora Nacional de Derechos Humanos (CNDDHH); Drug Policy Files; Human Rights Organizations and Cases; Vladimiro Montesinos Files; and Sendero Luminoso, or the Shining Path. Some materials have been moved to the Oversize Materials.
  The Coordinadora Nacional de Derechos Humanos Subseries contains internal files of the CNDDHH dated between 1985 and 2003. Included are files, reports, and research materials of the CNDDHH as well as partner organizations under its umbrella. Among the major organizations are the Asociación Nacional de Familiares de Secuestrados Detenidos y Desaparecidos del Perú (ANFASEP), the Asociación Pro Derechos Humanos (APRODEH), the Comisión de Derechos Humanos (CODEH), the Comisión Episcopal de Acción Social (CEAS), the Comisión Nacional de Derechos Humanos (CONADEH), Defensoria del Pueblo, and the Instituto Defensa Legal (IDL). Several theses or dissertations related to human rights in Perú are contained in this subseries, as are press releases (including photocopies of the CNDDHH publication Carta Circular from 1989-1998), and some email correspondence between Youngers and CNDDHH members. In addition to chronicling the activities of the CNDDHH and affiliated organizations, this subseries contains information on death threats received by CNDDHH leaders from the Grupo Colina, an extrajudicial death squad linked to former Peruvian President Alberto Fujimori and Vladimiro Montesinos, who controlled his security forces. Other topics covered in this subseries include human rights marches or demonstrations, "disappearances" and detentions of human rights advocates, and documentation of cases of torture by the government. One electronic file contains a 104-page report entitled 1° Informe Parcial Sobre La Situación De Derechos Humanos En El Perú, Febrero 2003, and is available to use on special request. Additional materials related to CNDDHH and other human rights organizations working in Perú as well as cases of human rights violations can be found in the Human Rights Organizations and Cases Subseries and in the Printed Material Series. Subseries is organized as received.
  The Drug Policy Files Subseries is primarily comprised of intelligence reports on narcotrafficking in Perú, the bulk of which are declassified documents from the US State Department and various intelligence organizations. In addition, files and reports from the Peruvian national drug control agency DEVIDA (Comisión Nacional para el Desarrollo y Vida sin Drogas) as well as Peruvian court and government documents are included. The role of the U.S. government in Perú as an observer, military advisor, and as an active counter-narcotics presence are documented. Some intelligence reports include information on the Sendero Luminoso as well as efforts to cripple the drug trade, both through military action and biologically through agents such as the fungus fusarium oxysporum (Agent Green). Vladimiro Montesinos and his relationship with drug traffickers are often featured prominently in this subseries. Organized as received.
  The Human Rights Organizations and Cases Subseries chiefly consists of magazine and newspaper clippings and press releases covering human rights abuses primarily by agents of the Peruvian military (and Grupo Colina) but also Sendero Luminoso. It contains informal reports as well as some email correspondence and press releases from WOLA and prominent Peruvian human rights organizations, including CNDDHH as well as ANFASEP, CEAS, El Comité Nacional de Familiares de Detenidos-Desaparecidos y Refugiados (COFADER), the Instituto Peruano de Educación en Derechos Humanos y la Paz (IPEDEHP), Defensoria del Pueblo, IDL, and the Instituto Educación Rural. Bound reports by Peruvian and international solidarity organizations generally are housed in the Printed Material Series. Material and communications from prominent international solidarity organizations such as Amnesty International and Human Rights Watch (as well as its subsidiary Americas Watch) appear in this subseries as well. Topics of note in this subseries include documentation and media coverage of detentions, torture, and "disappearances" of journalists and human rights activists, the 1985 prison riots, and well-known mass killings that took place at Los Barrios Altos, La Cantuta, Cayara, Chumbivilcas, and especially Uchuraccay. Subseries is organized as received.
  Montesinos' connections with United States intelligence services, drug trafficking, and human rights abuses are further explored in the Vladimiro Montesinos Files Subseries. In addition to declassified US government documents (which comprise the bulk of material in this subseries), this subseries contains a number of informal reports related to Montesinos by human rights organizations as well as numerous newspaper and magazine clippings. Files related to information on coup attempts against Alberto Fujimori, the MRTA Japanese embassy hostage crisis of 1996-1997, and the Montesinos bribery scandal that served as a catalyst for the collapse of the Fujimori government are included. Subseries is organized as received.
  The Sendero Luminoso Subseries contains clippings and files on the Maoist guerilla organization from 1982 through 1994 and undated. The bulk of the newspapers and clippings are from El Diario, an underground, Lima-based Communist publication affiliated with Sendero Luminoso. In addition, clippings from the Peruvian La Republica and prominent publications from the U.S. media are included. Beyond El Diario, the subseries does not contain many direct publications from Sendero's primarily rurally oriented operations, though there are several pieces of propaganda from unknown sources. Numerous draft publications of scholarly articles on Sendero Luminoso are included in this series; most of these are authored by U.S.-based researchers though some are from Latin American scholarly institutions. Together, the materials in this subseries chronicle Sendero Luminoso's early activities in Perú's rural mountain provinces through its acts of urban terrorism near the height of its power in the mid-1980s and finally the trial and imprisonment of leader Abimael Guzman after his capture in 1992. Subseries is organized by year.
  - Coordinadora Nacional de Derechos Humanos Subseries, 1985-2003 and undated, (56 folders) (Box 14-17)
    [Some items removed to Oversize Material. Contents of diskette migrated to server; please contact a Reference Archivist for assistance in accessing this material.]
  - Drug Policy Files Subseries, 1991-2004 and undated, (38 folders) (Box 17-19)
  - Human Rights Organizations and Cases Subseries, 1982-1999 and undated, (61 folders) (Box 20-23)
  - Vladimiro Montesinos Files Subseries, 1977-2003 and undated, (71 folders) (Box 24-28)
  - Sendero Luminoso Subseries, 1982-1994 and undated, (18 folders) (Box 29-30)
- Oversize Material, 1983-2002 and undated, (16 folders) (Box 29-30)
  The majority of this material originally was housed in the Subject Files Series, and consists of U.S.-based and Peruvian newspapers and clippings, which chronicle "disappearances" and killings of journalists and human rights workers (including clergy) in Perú, and contain numerous articles documenting several well-known mass killings. Many sections of newspapers - particularly El Diario, an underground, Lima-based Communist publication affiliated with Sendero Luminoso - document the activities of Sendero Luminoso. Articles on the state of Peruvian drug policy, government politics, and activities relating primarily to Alberto Fujimori and Vladimiro Montesinos, are also housed in Oversize Material. Other items include posters on women's rights in Perú and a packet of materials on rural citizens' rights. Arranged in order of main series and subseries sequence above. All folders except for Folder 3 have been boxed in Boxes 31 and 34.
  - Printed Material Series (Box 29-30)
    - Research Files Subseries (Box 29-30)
      - Cambio (newspaper), 1988 Sept. (Box 31)
  - Subject Files Series (Box 31)
    - Coordinadora Nacional de Derechos Humanos Subseries (Box 31)
      - CNDDHH Peruvian human rights movement map, undated (Box 34)
      - Campana Para Los Desaparecidos, 1988 Dec. (Box 34)
      - Women's rights posters, undated (Opaperfolder 3, Box 34)
    - Drug Policy Files Subseries (Box 34)
      - Newspapers and clippings, 1984-2002 (Box 34)
    - Human Rights Organizations and Cases Subseries (Box 34)
      - Files and clippings on Jaime Ayala and Sybila Arredondo, 1984-1985 (Box 34)
      - Uchuraccay and Cayara massacre files and clippings, 1983-1989 (Box 31)
      - La Cantuta investigation, 1993 (Box 31)
      - Detentions of human rights workers and general Perú information, 1983-1988 and undated (Box 31)
      - Assassinations and Franco death squad files, 1988-1989 (Box 31)
      - Nuns killed at Lurigancho, 1983 Dec. (Box 31)
      - Perú prison riots, 1986-1987 (Box 31)
    - Vladimiro Montesinos Files Subseries (Box 31)
      - Files and clippings on the military, judiciary, and SIN/SIE intelligence forces, 1998-1999 (Box 31)
      - General files on Montesinos and drug policy, 1996-2002 (Box 34)
    - Sendero Luminoso Subseries (Box 34)
      - Newspapers and clippings, 1983-1991 (Box 31)
      - New York Times Magazine, 1990 Dec. 2 (Box 31)
      - Newspapers and clippings, 1983-1991 and undated (Box 34)
      - Headline sheets, undated (Opaperfolder 3, Box 34)
- Accession (2008-0151) (CLOSED), 1985-2000, 2 Boxes (Box 34)
  Addition (2008-0151) (900 items; 1.2 lin. ft.; dated 1985-2000) includes internal documents from the Coordinadora Nacional de Derechos Humanos (Perú). Acquired as part of the Human Rights Archive.
  This addition is CLOSED for 25 years.
  - Coordinadora Archivo (Box 32)
  - IDL Evaluations (Box 32)
  - Coord: Internal Evaluations (Box 32)
  - Coord: Primer Encuentro (Box 32)
  - Coord: 1988 (Box 32)
  - Coord: 1985-1987 (Box 32)
  - Coord: 1989 (Box 32)
  - Coord: 1989 Encuentro, III Encuentro (Box 32)
  - Coord: 1990 (Box 32)
  - Coord: 1991 Encuentro, IV Encuentro (Box 32)
  - Discussion of DIH, 1991 (Box 32)
  - Coord: 1991 Meetings of CD (Box 32)
  - Coord: 1991-Capac Yupanqui Rocal Dispute (Box 32)
  - Coord: 1991/Various Communication (Box 32)
  - Coord: 1992 (Box 32)
  - Coord: Medicas de Comunicación, 1992-1994 (Box 33)
  - Coord: 1993 (Box 33)
  - Quinto Encuentro: 1993 (Box 33)
  - Coord: 1993 Reinscription (Box 33)
  - Coord: 1994 (Box 33)
  - Coord: 1995 (Box 33)
  - Coord: 1997 Encuentro, VII Encuentro (Box 33)
  - Coord: Informo/Actividades, 1997-1999 (Box 33)
  - Workplan, 1998-1999 (Box 33)
  - Coord: Workplans/Activities, 1993- (Box 33)
  - Journa's Interviews (Box 33)
  - AID Evaluation, April 2000 (Box 33)
  - Coordinadora List of Members (Box 33)
  - Evaluations by Sofia Lind. (Box 33)
  - Quinto Encuentro Nacional de Organismos de Derechos Humanos, 1993 (Box 33)
Separated Material
Books and Other Bound Volumes:
These items have been transferred to the Duke Perkins Library general collections; they can be located through the Duke Libraries online catalog.
Alvarez, Elena. Politica Economica y Agricultura en el Perú, 1969-1979. Lima, Perú: Instituto de Estudios Peruanos, 1983.
Amery, Jennifer and Roberto López. Medicamentos en el Perú: Comercialización y Consumo. Chimbote, Perú: Instituto de Promocion y Educacion Popular, 1985.
Arbulú, Javier Tantalean. Enemigos de la Democracia. Lima, Perú: 1994.